<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles concluded and agreed vpon by the Lords, the Cardinalls, de la Roche-Foucaud, and de Bethune, in the name of the King of France, to the Queene Mother Together with certaine letters interchangeably sent betweene the said king and the Queene-Mother. Translated out of the French copie.</title>
            <title>Articles accordez: par Messieurs le cardinal de la Roche-Foucault, et de Béthune, au nom du roy, a la Royne Mere. English.</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103957</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839699</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839699</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 845:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles concluded and agreed vpon by the Lords, the Cardinalls, de la Roche-Foucaud, and de Bethune, in the name of the King of France, to the Queene Mother Together with certaine letters interchangeably sent betweene the said king and the Queene-Mother. Translated out of the French copie.</title>
                  <title>Articles accordez: par Messieurs le cardinal de la Roche-Foucault, et de Béthune, au nom du roy, a la Royne Mere. English.</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1610-1643 : Louis XIII)</author>
                  <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 15, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. E[ld] for George Fairebeard, and are to bee sold at his shop at the north entrance into the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Articles accordez: par Messieurs le cardinal de la Roche-Foucault, et de Béthune, au nom du roy, a la Royne Mere.</note>
                  <note>With a frontispiece portrait of Louis XIII.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:4145:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>WIS THE XIII KING OF FRANCE.</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Louis XIII</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4145:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
            <p>ARTICLES CONCLVDED AND AGREED VPON by the Lords, the Cardinalls, <hi>de la Roche-Foucaud,</hi> and <hi>de Bethune,</hi> in the name of the King of <hi>France, to the Queene Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with certaine Letters</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably ſent betweene the ſaid King <hi>and the Queene-Mother</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the French Copie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>fleur-de-lis surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed by <hi>G. E.</hi> for <hi>George Fairebeard,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop at the North entrance into the Royall <hi>Exchange.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:4145:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4145:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <head>ARTICLES CONCLVDED AND agreed vpon by the Lords the Cardinals <hi>de la Roche-Foucaud</hi> and <hi>de Bethune,</hi> in the name of the King of FRANCE, to the Queene-Mother.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Maieſty agreeth and conſenteth, that the Queen Mother ſhall diſpoſe of her houſe, as it ſhall pleaſe her, calling vnto her and receiuing ſuch perſons into her ſeruice as ſhee thinketh good.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4145:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
2 THat Shee ſhall and may goe and come, and alſo ſoiourne in ſuch place or places of the Realme as Shee will, His Maieſties Court of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence not excepted.</p>
            <p n="3">3 THat during her life, Shee ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy whatſoeuer Shee hath hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enioyed, by Aſſignation, of Guifts, Penſions, and Gratifications to her giuen and granted by the late King, and by his Maieſty: and that Shee ſhall be paid all the Arrerages thereof what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4145:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
4 THat Shee ſhall freely diſpoſe not onely of the charges, Offices and benefits depending vppon and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to the Demaines, which her Maieſty at this preſent enioyeth, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of thoſe that were giuen vnto her for the full and perfect Aſſignation of her Matrimoniall Dowry, all conformable to the expedition which ſhe already hath.</p>
            <p n="5">5 HIs Maieſty promiſeth to deale friendly (as with other his Subiects and ſeruants) with all thoſe, that haue ſerued, ayded and aſſiſted the ſayd Queene, vppon occaſion of her retraict from Bloys, namely the Duke <hi>Deſpernon</hi> and his Children.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4145:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
6 THat his Maieſty will ſuffer them to enioy their Charges, Dignities, Offices, and Benefits, and reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them in all the Townes, Places, and Caſtles without any exception, where they find themſelues to bee diſpoſſeſſed, ſince the retraict of the Queene: and further that they ſhall bee payed their Penſions, Reuennues, and other Fees.</p>
            <p n="7">7 THat all thoſe that by Iudgement, or otherwiſe, haue beene baniſhed from the Court, or out of the Realme, ſhall bee recalled, and thoſe that are retayned priſoners, or are in priſon, ſhall bee releaſed and ſet at liberty.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4145:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
8 THat all whatſoeuer hath hapned or is paſt, by meanes of her Maieſties retraict from the Towne of Bloys, whether it ſhall bee leuying of Soldiers, Impoſitions, or Taxations of money, and other things whatſoeuer, ſhall be put in obliuion, without any renouation or calling in queſtion of any perſon for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="9">9 THat within two moneths, the ſaid Queene Mother ſhall bee ſatisfied and contented, for the disburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which ſhe hath beene conſtrained to make ſince her retraict to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouleſme.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4145:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
10 THat within ſixe weekes, the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Kings graunt to her made, ſhall bee verified and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in all the Courts of Parliament, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the forme and tenure thereof, without any reſtriction or moderation whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Made and promiſed in Angouleſme by the ſaid Lords, the Cardinall <hi>de la Roche-Foucaud</hi> and <hi>de Bethune,</hi> by vertue of their Commiſſion giuen them by the Kings Maieſty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, <hi>LOVYS.</hi>
               </signed> 
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>And allowed,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>PHILIPPE A VLX.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:4145:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
            <head>The King of France his Letter, written to the Queene-Mother, <date>the 3. of May. 1619.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of Father <hi>Berule,</hi> you ſhall know what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution I haue taken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the propoſitions by him made vnto mee. I aſſure my ſelfe, that when hee ſhall haue informed you of my intents, and the reaſons whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they are grounded: you will iudge and bee perſwaded, that I haue omitted nothing whatſoeuer I thought might procure the good of mine eſtate and your contentment, which ought to bee inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: but that which I ſpecially deſire and ayme at, is, that you ſhould beleeue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4145:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->and bee perſwaded, that you ſhall neuer find any thing to be truer then the effects of my affections, whereof I will ſeeke by all occaſions, to giue you ſo many proofs, that you ſhall perfectly ſee and know, that one of the things in this world which I moſt deſire, is, to ſee vs revnited in ſo perfect amity, and with intire wills and affections that wee may neuer haue other difference, but onely to ſtriue which of vs ſhall yeelde more vnto the other: you Madame of a good Mother, and my ſelfe of a moſt affectionate Son: which I am perſwaded, by the grace of God, I ſhall ſee happily performed, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming my ſelfe of your good nature, my conſcience warranting mee, that there wanteth no poynt of all thoſe reſpects whatſoeuer in me, which may iuſtly giue mee the Title and Name, MADAME, of your moſt humble &amp; obedient Sonne,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>LOVYS.</signed>
               <dateline>From St. Germain <date>the 3 of May 1619.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:4145:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
            <head>The Queene-Mothers Anſwer, ſent to the King of <hi>France,</hi> her Son, <date>the 28. of May. 1619.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y LORD my Sonne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I do giue thankes vnto God with all my heart, vppon this Feaſt of the Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that in my departure from Bloys, I had no other intent nor meaning but onely that which tended to the felicity and aduancement of your ſeruice, and a deſire to enioy the liberty of true Peace and quietnes, and that acknowledging it, you haue fully and intirely granted the ſame vnto mee, and giuen Peace vnto your people, diſcharging and vnburthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them of the troubles and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which they endured by meanes of the Souldiers, wherein as on the one ſide,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4145:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->I haue had ſo much reſpect, that I would not oppoſe thoſe forces that were prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the neceſſity of my defence, ſo I haue conceiued great pleaſure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to ſee that you haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the truth in this; that after my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traict, I oftentimes writ vnto you, that this running to Armes would wholely bee vnprofitable to you. I haue deferred to write vnto you, hoping from time to time, that to the comfort and ſolace of thoſe Prouinces and others vnder your obedience, you would bee pleaſed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge and remitte the Soldiers, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, (which it hath pleaſed you to ſend mee,) importeth, and whereof I ſpeake not as doubting the ſame, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your inuiolable word, proteſting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that concerning that which tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth my particular ſecurity: The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that I can haue in this world, and which alſo is moſt acceptable vnto mee, is, the affection which you promiſe mee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4145:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->by your laſt letters and whereof you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure mee, to giue mee ſuch proofes, as I ought to beleeue, that you haue thereby yeelded vnto mee that perfect amitie, which I alwayes procured and ſought to merit by al actions worthy of a moſt good Mother, and a moſt faithfull ſubiect. Therefore I truſt onely in your royall promiſe; and lay hold vppon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment which to mee is moſt eſſentiall, &amp; only can procure me all the reſt, among the which the principalleſt is, and ſhall be to ſee your authoritie more and more to encreaſe and proſper, and that not any perſon ſhall once dare to trouble the Peace and Tranquility of your Realme, which I deſire and wiſh, as much as the preſeruation of mine owne life, which I will continue vnder the onely Protection of your Maieſtie, inioying the free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by you graunted vnto mee, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing vnto you in all ſorts of occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as the Earle <hi>de Breſne</hi> will tell you)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4145:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->that I hold and eſteeme nothing ſo deare, as the paſſionate affection, my Lord my Sonne, which I haue to bee,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt louing mother and ſubiect, MARY.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Angouleſme</hi> 
                  <date>the 28 of May 1619.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:4145:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
            <head>A third Letter ſent by the Lord Admirall the Duke <hi>de Mont-morancy</hi> to the King of France.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The thankes which I am bound to yeeld vnto your Maieſty, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite fauours which it hath pleaſed you to ſhew vnto my Lord the Prince, which I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by his letter, and by the report of Monſieur <hi>de la Bauine,</hi> that it conſtraineth me by the exceſſe of bountie to yeelde witneſſe of the iuſt fe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling which I haue thereof, ſo that I cannot chooſe but ioyne them next vnto thoſe which I owe vnto God for his health, and to the moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thankes which I ſhortly hope to yeeld vnto your Maieſtie, for the perfection of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4145:9"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->a worke ſo fauourably begunne: as alſo the honor which it hath pleaſed the ſame to afford me, in putting that confidence in mee, to permit this Gentlman to tell him ſo much from mee, redoubleth my hopes, augmenteth my dueties, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth mee, ſtill without ceaſing, to continue my moſt humble and moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant prayers and ſupplications in this ſubiect, which may bring ſo great a good and benefit to your ſeruice, and much and ſo ſound a reputation to your bountie: my Vncle <hi>de Diſsimieux</hi> hath already made your Maieſtie acquainted with the State of this Prouince, where the effects of my fidelity God be thanked (are ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the ſhadowes that are impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on them by ſome) that I thinke and aſſure my ſelfe, that it would bee a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh to the innocencie of my actions and thoughts: If I ſhould enter into any other iuſtification, then onely by a new oath made, to continue in my obedience, with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4145:9"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->an affection anſwerable to my indeuours wherein I will expect the ſucceſſe of the negociation of my Lords the Cardinals <hi>de la Roche-Foucaud,</hi> and <hi>de Bethune,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God with all my heart, that it may fall out to the contentment of your Maieſtie, and the Peace of your ſubiects, to whom the ſame euidently declareth the deſire and the care that it hath of their good: For my part I ſhall neuer bee ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in that deſire that I haue to teſtifie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Maieſtie, that I am and alwayes ſhall bee,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, moſt obedient, and moſt faithfull ſubiect and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant. L. De <hi>Mont-morency.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From Beziers <date>the 24. of May 1619.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
